Over our lifetimes,
خلال مسيرة حياتنا
we've all contributed to climate change.
ساهم كل منا بتغير المناخ.
Actions, choices and behaviors
ممارساتنا وخياراتنا وتصرفاتنا
will have led to an increase in greenhouse gas emissions.
أدت إلى زيادة في انبعاث الغازات الدفيئة.
And I think that that's quite a powerful thought.
وأنا أعتقد أنه لشيء عظيم التفكير بهذه الطريقة.
But it does have the potential to make us feel guilty
ولكن لهذا التفكير المقدرة على جعلنا نشعر بالذنب
when we think about decisions we might have made
عندما نفكر بقرارات قد اتخذناها سابقاً
around where to travel to,
عن الأماكن التي نريد السفر إليها،
how often and how,
كم مرة و كيف نريد السفر،
about the energy that we choose to use
عن نوع الطاقة التي اخترنا استخدامها
in our homes or in our workplaces,
في منازلنا أو في أماكن عملنا،
or quite simply the lifestyles that we lead and enjoy.
أو بكل بساطة اختيار نمط الحياة الذي يشعرنا بالمتعة .
But we can also turn that thought on its head,
لكن, يمكننا أيضاَ قلب هذه الفكرة رأسا على عقب،
and think that if we've had such a profound
والتفكير بأنه في صورة وجود هذا التأثير العميق
but a negative impact on our climate already,
ولكن السلبي على مناخنا،
then we have an opportunity to influence the amount of future climate change
فلدينا الفرصة للتأثير على مدى التغُّير الذي سيطرأ على المناخ في المستقبل
that we will need to adapt to.
والذي يجب علينا التأقلم معه .
So we have a choice.
إذاً لدينا الاختيار.
We can either choose to start to take climate change seriously,
بإمكاننا إما اختيار أخذ فكرة تغير المناخ على محمل الجد،
and significantly cut and mitigate our greenhouse gas emissions,
والتخفيف بشكل ملحوظ من انبعاث الغازات الدفيئة،
and then we will have to adapt to less of the climate change impacts in future.
ومن ثم سنقوم بالتأقلم مع انخفاض آثار تغير المناخ في المستقبل.
Alternatively, we can continue to really ignore the climate change problem.
بدلا من ذلك، بإمكاننا مواصلة تجاهل مشكلة تغير المناخ.
But if we do that, we are also choosing
ولكن إذا قمنا بذلك، فنحن أيضا نختار
to adapt to very much more powerful climate impacts in future.
التأقلم مع آثار كبيرة للمناخ في المستقبل.
And not only that.
وليس ذلك فقط.
As people who live in countries with high per capita emissions,
كأشخاص يعيشون في بلدان مع نسبة انبعاثات عالية لكل فرد،
we're making that choice on behalf of others as well.
نحن نقوم بهذا الاختيار في صالح الآخرين أيضا.
But the choice that we don't have
ولكن الاختيار الذي لا يلزم أخذه
is a no climate change future.
هو عدم تغيير المناخ في المستقبل.
Over the last two decades,
على مدى العقدين الماضيين،
our government negotiators and policymakers have been coming together
مفاوضو حكومتنا وصانعو القرار اجتمعوا معا
to discuss climate change,
لمناقشة تغير المناخ،
and they've been focused on avoiding a two-degree centigrade warming
ولقد ركّزوا على تجنب ارتفاع درجة الحرارة بدرجتين
above pre-industrial levels.
فوق المستويات ما قبل الثورة الصناعية.
That's the temperature that's associated with dangerous impacts
هذه هي درجة الحرارة المرتبطة بالأثار الخطيرة
across a range of different indicators,
عبر مجموعة من الأثار المختلفة،
to humans and to the environment.
على الإنسان والبيئة.
So two degrees centigrade constitutes dangerous climate change.
إذن يُمثّل ارتفاع درج الحرارة بدرجتين تغير مناخي خطير.
But dangerous climate change can be subjective.
ولكن من الممكن أن يكون تغير المناخ الخطير غير موضوعيا.
So if we think about an extreme weather event
إذن إذا فكرنا في حدث متعلق بسوء الأحوال الجوية
that might happen in some part of the world,
والذي من الممكن أن يحدث في أي مكان في العالم،
and if that happens in a part of the world where there is good infrastructure,
وإذا حدث ذلك في مكان حيث البنية التحتية جيدة،
where there are people that are well-insured and so on,
وحيث يتم تأمين الناس جيدا وما إلى ذلك،
then that impact can be disruptive.
إذن من الممكن أن يكون تأثير ذلك مزعجا.
It can cause upset, it could cause cost.
من الممكن أن يتسبب في الجزع وأن يكون مكلفا.
It could even cause some deaths.
من المرجح أيضا أن يتسبب في عدد من الوفيات.
But if that exact same weather event happens in a part of the world
ولكن إذا صار نفس الحدث المتعلق بسوء الأحوال الجوية
where there is poor infrastructure,
في مكان من العالم ذو بنية تحتية ضعيفة،
or where people are not well-insured,
أو حيث لا تتوفر حماية جيدة للأشخاص،
or they're not having good support networks,
أو لا يملكون شبكات دعم جيدة،
then that same climate change impact could be devastating.
إذن أثر تغير المناخ من الممكن أن يكون مدمرا.
It could cause a significant loss of home,
من الممكن أن يتسبب في خسارة الناس لمنازلهم،
but it could also cause significant amounts of death.
كما يمكن أن يتسبب في وفات العديد من الأشخاص.
So this is a graph of the CO2 emissions at the left-hand side
إذن هذا الرسم البياني على يساري لانبعاث ثاني أكسيد الكربون
from fossil fuel and industry,
من الوقود الأحفوري والأعمال الصناعية،
and time from before the Industrial Revolution
ويرجع هذا إلى ما قبل الثورة الصناعية
out towards the present day.
إلى يومنا هذا.
And what's immediately striking about this
ولكن المدهش بخصوص هذا
is that emissions have been growing exponentially.
بأن هذه الانبعاثلت في ارتفاع تصاعدي.
If we focus in on a shorter period of time from 1950,
إذا ركزنا على فترة قصيرة من 1950،
we have established in 1988
في سنة 1988، قمنا بإنشاء
the Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change,
لجنة مشتركة بين الحكومات حول تغير المناخ،
the Rio Earth Summit in 1992,
قمّة الأرض بريو سنة 1992،
then rolling on a few years, in 2009 we had the Copenhagen Accord,
ثم بعد بضعة سنوات في سنة 2009 كان لدينا اتفاقية كوبنهاجن،
where it established avoiding a two-degree temperature rise
والتي اهتمت بكيفية تجنب ارتفاع الحرارة بدرجتين
in keeping with the science and on the basis of equity.
وفقا للعلوم وأساس العدل.
And then in 2012, we had the Rio+20 event.
وثم في سنة 2012، كان لدينا حدث ريو+20.
And all the way through, during all of these meetings
وخلال كل هذه المقابلات
and many others as well,
ومقابلات أخرى كذلك،
emissions have continued to rise.
مازالت الانبعاثات في ارتفاع.
And if we focus on our historical emission trend in recent years,
وإذا ركزنا على نسق الانبعاث عبر التاريخ خلال السنوات الأخيرة،
and we put that together with our understanding
وأضفنا ذلك إلى فهمنا
of the direction of travel in our global economy,
لمسار اقتصادنا العالمي،
then we are much more on track
فنحن نتتبع بشكل أكبر
for a four-degree centigrade global warming
الاحتباس الحراري ذي الأربع درجات
than we are for the two-degree centigrade.
بالمقارنة من معدل الدرجتين.
Now, let's just pause for a moment
والآن، لنأخذ استراحة لمدة وجيزة
and think about this four-degree global average temperature.
ونفكر في متوسط درجات الحرارة المقدر بأربع درجات.
Most of our planet is actually made up of the sea.
معظم كوكبنا هو في الحقيقة متكون من البحر.
Now, because the sea has a greater thermal inertia than the land,
الآن، لأن للماء قصور ذاتي أكبر من الأرض،
the average temperatures over land are actually going to be higher
معدلات الحرارة على الأرض ستكون في الحقيقة أعلى
than they are over the sea.
من تلك في البحر.
The second thing is that we as human beings don't experience
والشيء الثاني هو أننا نحن كبشر لا نختبر
global average temperatures.
معدل الحرارة العالمي.
We experience hot days, cold days,
نختبر أياما ساخنة وأياما باردة،
rainy days, especially if you live in Manchester like me.
أياما ممطرة، خاصة إن كنتم تعيشون في منشستر مثلي.
So now put yourself in a city center.
والآن ضع نفسك في وسط المدينة.
Imagine somewhere in the world:
تخيل أي مكان في العالم:
Mumbai, Beijing, New York, London.
مومباي، بكين، نيويورك أو لندن.
It's the hottest day that you've ever experienced.
إنه أسخن يوم اختبرته.
There's sun beating down,
الشمس ساطعة،
there's concrete and glass all around you.
يوجد الإسمنت والزجاج من حولك.
Now imagine that same day --
والآن تخيل نفس اليوم --
but it's six, eight, maybe 10 to 12 degrees warmer
ولكن الحرارة أعلى بست، ثمان ربما عشر إلى 12 درجة
on that day during that heat wave.
في ذلك اليوم خلال موجة الحرارة.
That's the kind of thing we're going to experience
هذا هو نوع الأشياء التي سنختبرها
under a four-degree global average temperature scenario.
خلال سيناريو معدل درجة الحرارة تحت أربع درجات.
And the problem with these extremes,
والمشكل بدرجات الحرارة القصوى،
and not just the temperature extremes,
وليس فقط درجات الحرارة القصوى،
but also the extremes in terms of storms and other climate impacts,
ولكن أيضا في ما يتعلق بالعواصف والآثار الأخرى للمناخ،
is our infrastructure is just not set up to deal with these sorts of events.
لا يتم تصميم البنية التحتية للتعامل مع هذا النوع من الأحداث.
So our roads and our rail networks
إذن تم تصميم طرقاتنا وشبكاتنا الحديدية
have been designed to last for a long time
لتدوم فترة طويلة
and withstand only certain amounts of impacts
وتحمل قدر معين من الأثار
in different parts of the world.
في جميع أنحاء العالم.
And this is going to be extremely challenged.
وهذا سيكون تحديا خطيرا.
Our power stations are expected to be cooled by water
من المتوقع أن يتم تبريد محطات الطاقة بالماء
to a certain temperature to remain effective and resilient.
للوصول لدرجة حرارة معينة لتظل فعّالة ومرنة.
And our buildings are designed to be comfortable
ولقد تم تصميم مبانينا لتكون مريحة
within a particular temperature range.
في درجة حرارة معينة.
And this is all going to be significantly challenged
وسيكون كل هذا تحديا
under a four-degree-type scenario.
خلال سيناريو أقل بأربع درجات.
Our infrastructure has not been designed to cope with this.
لم يتم تصميم بنيتنا التحتية للتعامل مع هذا.
So if we go back, also thinking about four degrees,
اذن، إذا رجعنا للوراء وفكرنا في الدرجات الأربع،
it's not just the direct impacts,
ليس فقط التأثير المباشر،
but also some indirect impacts.
ولكن أيضا بعض التأثيرات غير المباشرة.
So if we take food security, for example.
إذا أخذنا على سبيل المثال، سلامة الأغذية.
Maize and wheat yields
محاصيل الذرة والقمح
in some parts of the world
في بعض أنحاء العالم
are expected to be up to 40 percent lower
من المتوقع أن تكون أقل ب40%
under a four-degree scenario,
في سيناريو أقل بأربع درجات،
rice up to 30 percent lower.
والأرز أقل ب30%.
This will be absolutely devastating for global food security.
سيكون هذا مدمرا للأمن الغذائي العالمي.
So all in all, the kinds of impacts anticipated
إذن في المجمل، أنواع الأثار المتوقعة
under this four-degree centigrade scenario
لسيناريو أقل بأربع درجات مئوية
are going to be incompatible with global organized living.
ستكون مختلفة مع المعيشة المنظمة العالمية.
So back to our trajectories and our graphs of four degrees and two degrees.
إذن بالرجوع إلى الرسوم البيانية المتعلقة بالأربع درجات والدرجتين.
Is it reasonable still to focus on the two-degree path?
هل من المعقول التركيز على الدرجتين؟
There are quite a lot of my colleagues and other scientists
العديد من زملائي وعلماء آخرون
who would say that it's now too late to avoid a two-degree warming.
صرحوا بأنه حاليا سيكون تجنب ارتفاع درجة الحرارة بدرجتين متأخرا.
But I would just like to draw on my own research
ولكنني أريد أن أقوم ببحثي
on energy systems, on food systems,
حول أنظمة الطاقة وأنظمة الأغذية،
aviation and also shipping,
والطيران وكذلك الملاحة،
just to say that I think there is still a small fighting chance
للذكر فقط، أعتقد أنه ماتزال توجد فرصة محاربة صغيرة
of avoiding this two-degree dangerous climate change.
لتجنب تغير المناخ الخطير بدرجتين.
But we really need to get to grips with the numbers
ولكننا حقا في حاجة لمجابهة هذه الأرقام
to work out how to do it.
لمعرفة كيفية العمل على ذلك.
So if you focus in on this trajectory and these graphs,
إذن إذا ركزتم على هذه الرسوم البيانية،
the yellow circle there highlights that the departure
تُبيّن تلك الدائرة الصفراء أن البداية
from the red four-degree pathway
من المسلك الأحمر للأربع درجات
to the two-degree green pathway is immediate.
إلى المسلك الأخضر للدرجتين، فورية.
And that's because of cumulative emissions,
وذلك بسبب الانبعاثات المتراكمة،
or the carbon budget.
أو كميّة الكربون.
So in other words, because of the lights and the projectors
إذن بمعنى آخر، بسبب الأضواء وأجهزة العرض
that are on in this room right now,
الموجودة الآن بالغرفة،
the CO2 that is going into our atmosphere
ثاني أكسيد الكربون المنبعث في جونا
as a result of that electricity consumption
الناتج عن استهلاك الكهرباء
lasts a very long time.
يدوم طويلا.
Some of it will be in our atmosphere for a century, maybe much longer.
البعض منه سيظلّ لقرن، أو ربما أكثر من ذلك بقليل.
It will accumulate, and greenhouse gases tend to be cumulative.
سوف يتراكم، كما ستميل الغازات الدفيئة إلى التراكم.
And that tells us something about these trajectories.
وهذا يدلّنا على مساراتها.
First of all, it tells us that it's the area under these curves that matter,
أولا، تخبرنا بأن هذه المنطقة تحت المنحنيات هي المهمة،
not where we reach at a particular date in future.
وليس ما نصل إليه في تاريخ معين في المستقبل.
And that's important, because it doesn't matter
وهذا مهم، لأنه لا يهم
if we come up with some amazing whiz-bang technology
إن أتينا ببعض التكنولجيات الرائعة والناجحة
to sort out our energy problem on the last day of 2049,
لتصنيف مشكلتنا المتعلقة بالطاقة في اليوم الأخير من 2049.
just in the nick of time to sort things out.
فقط في الوقت المناسب لتصنيف الأشياء.
Because in the meantime, emissions will have accumulated.
لأنه في هذه الأثناء، ستتراكم الانبعاثات.
So if we continue on this red, four-degree centigrade scenario pathway,
إذن في صورة مواصلتنا في سيناريو المسلك الأحمر للأربع درجات،
the longer we continue on it,
كلما واصلنا في ذلك،
that will need to be made up for in later years
فستحتاج معالجته خلال السنوات المقبلة
to keep the same carbon budget, to keep the same area under the curve,
للمحافظة على نفس كمية الكربون، وعلى نفس المنطقة تحت المنحنيات،
which means that that trajectory, the red one there, becomes steeper.
مما يعني أن هذا المسار، الأحمر، سيصبح حادّا.
So in other words, if we don't reduce emissions in the short to medium term,
يعني، إن لم نقم بتخفيض الانبعاثات على المدى القصير أو المتوسط،
then we'll have to make more significant year-on-year emission reductions.
فسيكون من المهم القيام بتخفيضات هامة من سنة إلى أخرى.
We also know that we have to decarbonize our energy system.
كما نعرف بأنه علينا تخليص نظامنا للطاقة من الكربون.
But if we don't start to cut emissions in the short to medium term,
ولكن إن لم نقم بقطع الانبعاثات على المدى القصير أو المتوسط،
then we will have to do that even sooner.
فسيتوجب علينا القيام بذلك في أقرب وقت ممكن.
So this poses really big challenges for us.
لذلك فإن هذا سيضعنا أمام مجموعة من التحديات الكبيرة.
The other thing it does is tells us something about energy policy.
والشيء الثاني الذي يقوم به هو إخبارنا بأمر ما حول سياسة الطاقة.
If you live in a part of the world where per capita emissions are already high,
إذا كنت تعيش في مكان في العالم حيث نسبة الانبعاثات للفرد الواحد مرتفعة أصلا،
it points us towards reducing energy demand.
فإن ذلك سيوجّهنا حول تخفيض طلب الطاقة.
And that's because with all the will in the world,
وذلك لأنه مع كل تلك الإرادة في العالم،
the large-scale engineering infrastructure
فإن الهندسة للبنية التحتية على نطاق واسع
that we need to roll out rapidly
والتي نحن بحاجة إليها بسرعة
to decarbonize the supply side of our energy system
لإزالة الكربون من أجهزة نظام الطاقة
is just simply not going to happen in time.
لن تتم بكل بساطة في الوقت المناسب.
So it doesn't matter whether we choose nuclear power
لذلك لا يهم ما إذا اخترنا الطاقة النووية
or carbon capture and storage,
أوضبطنا الكربون وخزناه،
upscale our biofuel production,
أو زدنا في سعر الوقود الحيوي،
or go for a much bigger roll-out of wind turbines and wave turbines.
أوذهبنا إلى أبعد من ذلك، ونشرما توربينات الرياح والموجات.
All of that will take time.
كل هذا سيستغرق وقتا.
So because it's the area under the curve that matters,
لذلك بما أن تلك المنطقة تحت الإنحناءات التي تهمّ،
we need to focus on energy efficiency,
فنحن نحتاج إلى التركيز على فعالية الطاقة،
but also on energy conservation -- in other words, using less energy.
ولكن أيضا على المحافظة على الطاقة، أي استعمال أقل للطاقة.
And if we do that, that also means
وإذا قمنا بذلك، فذلك يعني أيضا
that as we continue to roll out the supply-side technology,
بأننا سنواصل نشر جوانب التكنولوجيا،
we will have less of a job to do if we've actually managed
سوف يكون لدينا عمل أقل إذا تمكنا من العمل
to reduce our energy consumption,
على تخفيض استهلاكنا للطاقة،
because we will then need less infrastructure on the supply side.
لأننا سنحتاج إلى بنية تحتية أقل خلال العرض.
Another issue that we really need to grapple with
قضية أخرى نحتاج إلى التصدي لها
is the issue of well-being and equity.
هي قضية الرفاه والعدل.
There are many parts of the world where the standard of living needs to rise.
يوجد العديد من المناطق في العالم حيث يجب وضع معايير للعيش.
Bbut with energy systems currently reliant on fossil fuel,
وبما أن أنظمة الطاقة تعتمد على الوقود الأحفوري،
as those economies grow so will emissions.
كلما تنمو الإقتصادات كلما تنمو الانبعاثات.
And now, if we're all constrained by the same amount of carbon budget,
والآن، إذا كنا كلنا مقيدين بنفس كمية الكربون،
that means that if some parts of the world's emissions are needing to rise,
هذا يعني أنه في بعض أجزاء العالم هناك انبعاثات ينبغي أن ترتفع،
then other parts of the world's emissions need to reduce.
وبالتالي بمناطق أخرى من العالم ينبغي أن تنخفض هذه الانبعاثات.
So that poses very significant challenges for wealthy nations.
وهذا يمثّل تحديات كبيرة جدا بالنسبة للدول الغنية.
Because according to our research,
لأنه وفقا لأبحاثنا،
if you're in a country where per capita emissions are really high --
إذا كنت ببلد حيث تكون نسبة انبعاثات للفرد الواحد مرتفعة جدا --
so North America, Europe, Australia --
أمريكا الشمالية وأروربا وأستراليا --
emissions reductions of the order of 10 percent per year,
فإن خفض الانبعاثات ب10% بالمائة في السنة،
and starting immediately, will be required for a good chance
وفي حال بدأنا فورا، سيكون أمرا ضروريا لنحظى بفرصة جيدة
of avoiding the two-degree target.
لتجنب هدف الدرجتين.
Let me just put that into context.
دعوني أضع ذلك ضمن السياق.
The economist Nicholas Stern
الخبير الإقتصادي نيكولاس ستيرن
said that emission reductions of more than one percent per year
صرّح بأن انخفاض الانبعاثات أكثر من 1% في السنة
had only ever been associated with economic recession or upheaval.
لم يكن أبدا مرتبطا بالركود الإقتصادي أو الإضطراب.
So this poses huge challenges for the issue of economic growth,
إذن فهذا يمثّل تحديا لمسألة النمو الإقتصادي،
because if we have our high carbon infrastructure in place,
لأنه لو توفرت بنية تحتية للكربون
it means that if our economies grow,
هذا يعني أن اقتصادنا في نمو،
then so do our emissions.
وبالتالي انبعاثاتنا.
So I'd just like to take a quote from a paper
أريد فقط أن أقتبس مقولة من وثيقة
by myself and Kevin Anderson back in 2011
لي ولكيفن أندرسن في 2011
where we said that to avoid the two-degree framing of dangerous climate change,
حيث قلنا لتجنب تكون التغير المناخي الخطير "بدرجتين" ،
economic growth needs to be exchanged at least temporarily
نحتاج إلى تحدّي النمو الاقتصادي على الأقل مؤقتا
for a period of planned austerity in wealthy nations.
لفترة من التقشّف المُخطط له في الدول الغنية.
This is a really difficult message to take,
هذه رسالة صعبة،
because what it suggests is that we really need to do things differently.
لأن ما تقترحه هو الحاجة إلى القيام بالأشياء بطريقة أخرى.
This is not about just incremental change.
هذا ليس مجرد تغيير تدريجي.
This is about doing things differently, about whole system change,
يتعلق الأمر هنا بالقيام بالأشياء بطريقة مغايرة،حول نظام التغيير الكلي،
and sometimes it's about doing less things.
وفي بعض الأحيان القيام بأشياء أقل.
And this applies to all of us,
وهذا ينطبق علينا جميعا،
whatever sphere of influence we have.
مهما كان مجال التأثير.
So it could be from writing to our local politician
من الممكن أن يكون الكتابة إلى سياسي محلي
to talking to our boss at work or being the boss at work,
إلى التحدث مع رئيسنا في العمل، أو أن تكون الرئيس في العمل،
or talking with our friends and family, or, quite simply, changing our lifestyles.
أو التكلم مع أصدقائنا وعائلتنا، أو بكل بساطة تغيير أنماط حياتنا.
Because we really need to make significant change.
لأننا في حاجة إلى القيام بتغيير ذي معنى.
At the moment, we're choosing a four-degree scenario.
حاليا، نحن نختار سيناريو الأربع درجات.
If we really want to avoid the two-degree scenario,
إذا كنا نريد تجنب سيناريو الدرجتين،
there really is no time like the present to act.
لا يوجد وقت أفضل من الآن للتحرك.
Thank you.
شكرا لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Bruno Giussani: Alice, basically what you're saying,
برونو غيوساني: أليس، ما قلته أساسا،
the talk is, unless wealthy nations start cutting 10 percent per year
فالرسالة هي، مالم تبدأ البلدان الغنية في تخفيض الانبعاثات بنسبة 10 في المئة في السنة
the emissions now, this year, not in 2020 or '25,
حاليا وليس في 2020 أو 2025.
we are going to go straight to the four-plus-degree scenario.
سوف نذهب مباشرة لسيناريو فوق الأربع درجات.
I am wondering what's your take on the cut by 70 percent for 2070.
أنا أتساءل ماهو رأيك بانخفاض بنسبة 70% في سنة 2070.
Alice Bows-Larkin: Yeah, it's just nowhere near enough to avoid two degrees.
أليس باوز لركين: نعم، إنها أبعد ما يكون لتجنب الدرجتين.
One of the things that often --
أحد الأشياء التي دائما --
when there are these modeling studies that look at what we need to do,
عندما توجد دراسات النماذج التي تهتم بما يجب القيام به،
is they tend to hugely overestimate how quickly other countries in the world
هي الميل إلى المبالغة في تقدير سرعة البلدان الأخرى في العالم
can start to reduce emissions.
لتبدأ في تخفيض التدفقات.
So they make kind of heroic assumptions about that.
إذن هم يقومون بنوع من الافتراضات البطولية حول ذلك.
The more we do that, because it's the cumulative emissions,
كلما قمنا بذلك، لأنها انبعاثات متراكمة،
the short-term stuff that really matters.
كلما تبين أن الأشياء على المدى القصير هي ما يهم حقا.
So it does make a huge difference.
حيث يُحدث ذلك فرقا كبيرا.
If a big country like China, for example,
إذا كان بلد كبير مثل الصين:
continues to grow even for just a few extra years,
سيستمر في النمو، حتى لعدة سنوات قليلة ،
that will make a big difference to when we need to decarbonize.
سيُحدث هذا فرقا كبيرا عند حاجتنا للتخلّص من الكربون.
So I don't think we can even say when it will be,
إذن أعتقد أنه لا يمكننا حتى القول متى سيكون ذلك،
because it all depends on what we have to do in the short term.
لأن ذلك كله يعتمد على ما لدينا على المدى القصير.
But I think we've just got huge scope, and we don't pull those levers
ولكن أعتقد أننا حصلنا الآن على هدف ضخم ولن نقوم بجذب الرافعة
that allow us to reduce the energy demand, which is a shame.
التي ستمكننا من تخفيض الطلب على الطاقة وهذا عار.
BG: Alice, thank you for coming to TED and sharing this data.
برونو غيوساني: شكرا لقدومك لTED ومشاركتنا هذه البيانات.
ABL: Thank you.
أليس باوز لركين: شكرا لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)